All right, welcome everybody. Thanks for
coming. Uh, we're going to be showing a
lot of code at the beginning on this
screen. So, if you're in the back, you
may want to move forward so you can see
that a little better. Uh, so here's the
agenda for the next two hours. We're
going to start with a short presentation
about the things that you're going to
then build hands-on the technologies and
that's just to give you an overview help
help you kind of understand all the
pieces because there's a lot of moving
pieces and we'll explain things as we go
and then after we do that 25minut
presentation then we're going to set you
loose onto a hands-on lab. Uh for that
you just need your laptop and a browser
and access to the Wi-Fi which is up on
the walls there. Uh everything else is
going to be provided for you in a cloud
environment. So we've got AWS accounts
provisioned for you that'll give you
access to the Bedrock service which
we'll talk about and all that. So um so
we're going to get hands-on that's in
about 25 minutes.
>> Yeah.
>> Anything else logistically?
>> I have questions. How many of you have
used Java?
>> How many of you use Spring?
>> Okay.
>> Great.
>> Oh boy.
>> Yeah. So you're going to learn some
Spring today.
>> A little bit. A little bit. All right.
Uh, yeah. So, we don't have anything up
there. That's awkward.
>> Still the
>> Can we have our screen?
>> There.
>> There we go.
>> This is our slide.
>> That's the only slide.
>> So, this whole time they were talking,
they didn't know I wasn't prepared.
>> Like I I was like I quickly switched
over to the slide thinking, "Oh, how
embarrassing. They saw our notes."
>> Yeah.
>> And And they didn't.
>> And I've just given away the game.
>> Okay. That's a bummer. Hey, look. Uh uh
that's James Ward. I'm Josh Long. And
we're we're we're very online. You can
find us on the internet. How many of you
are on the interneth?
Yeah. It's not it's not a great place to
be these days. Wow. What about what a
show? You know what? We just bumped into
Josh freaking McKente, one of my old
colleagues at Pivotal from years ago.
What? Like legend. And then Patrick
Dewis, another legend. Like this
conference is you know crazy.
>> We're the B team. It's okay.
>> Ah
so good. Um, yeah, amazing, amazing
show. So, uh, that's James. I'm Josh.
Like I said, we're the B team. You can
find us online. Um,
code is going to be here. Basically,
some of it, we're not going to be able
to cover all the code that's in that git
repository. Uh, but you can find the
bits there. And, uh, not a lot of you
using Spring, huh?
>> We can do a little
>> I think we should do a quick like
>> like five minutes.
>> Five. Can we do five minutes? Do five
minutes.
>> Five minutes.
>> Okay. Okay. Okay. So, let's talk let's
do some let's establish some basics here
because I'm scared that uh we're going
to dive right into it and we're going to
make assumptions that we shouldn't make
uh what with our vantage point being a
little different from yours if you
haven't done uh Java and Spring before.
So, we're going to build an application
here very quickly uh by going to my
second favorite place on the internet.
Obviously, my first favorite place is
and has always been he doesn't remember
production, right? So the best place on
the internet, best place on the in the
world, better than Disneyland, h
happiest place on earth. And uh
obviously, you know, start here. If you
haven't been to production, start here.
Okay? And we're going to build an
application, just a very simple
application, start.spring.io. Uh we're
going to use uh we have to I'm just
going to call this application because
again, I'm I'm amazing with names. We're
going to use Java 25 uh uh because
that's the only correct version of Java
to be using today. Right? You see here,
we have two radio boxes. These other
radio boxes are for the are from the
distant distant past. We don't ever
recommend that you use these. Uh these
are here just to know who makes terrible
life decisions. You should never ever
select these versions of Java. Right? So
we're gonna use Java 25. And um I'm
going to just add a very simple
application here. Gravium native image
support. Maybe we'll build a web service
here very quickly. And what we're going
to do is we're just going to build a
little simple Spring application.
Nothing to do with AI just yet because I
want you to understand that
fundamentally there's this framework
called Spring which underpins everything
that we're looking at today. And Spring
in turn uh gives you the ability to wire
your objects up. Why would you need a
framework to do that? Why can't you just
create these objects yourself and wire
them together manually? I mean, you
could, but the the the benefit of having
the framework do it is that it can give
you a little bit of a slight of hand, a
little bit of indirection. You you
create a thing of type fu, you ask for a
thing of type fu over here. In between,
somebody reworks that fu and gives you
extra capabilities. that indirection,
that ability to take what you've asked,
what you've produced, add things to it,
and then give it to you, and have it be
polymorphically compatible. That's a
superpower, right? And the reason that's
interesting is because Java is an
object-oriented language.
Object-oriented languages, you know, you
think about a single responsibility
principle, right? I've got an object. It
does one thing. It's my business logic.
Well, what if I want to add new
capabilities? I want to add auditing. I
want to add security. I want to add uh,
you know, observability. All that kind
of stuff. If I add these concerns, those
are orthogonal to my business logic. So,
how would you model that in an
object-oriented language? Maybe you
create a subclass and I guess if you
have three different concerns, you
create three different subasses and it
gets very tedious, right? You end up
with this deep hierarchy of sort of
redundant code and that that code that
you're going to write to to handle those
concerns that gets restipulated on each
new object that you create. So rather
than do that uh what we can do is we can
introduce those behaviors those
decorative concerns in a generic way
using one of the three pillars of spring
which is aspectoriented programming. So
aspect can you see that back there in
the galley? Okay
>> that's a good size right
>> aspect oriented programming.
>> We also have dependency
injection which is basically just you
know using constructors which is not a
big not a very big deal. And we have
portable service abstraction. So we have
this um this idea that spring provides
you with abstractions that make working
with lower level infrastructure less
painful. So these three tentpole pillars
are part of the spring triangle we used
to call that right and um nowadays we
also have this thing called spring boot
and spring boot takes it a step further
and adds a new thing called auto
configuration. So I suppose now it's
more of the spring square because you
got four points there, right? Or spring
rectangle, right? And so these four
things allow you to like solve a lot of
different problems. But let's just see
what I mean by that in action, right? So
let's say I have a let's just get rid of
all this stuff here. I'm going to make
that expand that out. Uh and um and by
the way, I mentioned I'm using Java 25,
right? This is very important to make
make sure we understand. I went to start
that swing. I chose Java 25. I'm using
Java 25. Java 25 is amazing. It allows
me to do one of my all-time favorite
tricks. uh and and and and
accomplishments ever. So, I'm going to
open that up. Okay, gonna write some
Java code in here as I'm want to do.
Okay, I'm going to write that out and
I'm going to run this. Okay, so here we
go. That's There we go. I ran that. Now,
that's a script that I wrote. I didn't
compile it. I didn't run Java C. I just
ran Java and I passed in the script
code, right? The code that I wanted to
run there. And so, what I've done is
I've run that. And a couple things to
note. First of all, this script um you
know there's no outer class, right?
There's no no containing type. In fact,
the void main method is also just very
trivial, very easy to understand. Void
main, curly bracket, curly bracket. So,
it's very very lightweight. There's no
containing class. It is uh like me
classless. Okay? And um it's also a
script, right? And so what this is is
it's a script that's been written in
Java. And you know what that means?
Think about this. Just enjoy this
moment. For the first time, for the
first time in 30 plus years, we have a
good JavaScript. Okay, this hasn't been
done before. It hasn't been done before.
There's no such thing as good JavaScript
before this feature arrived in Java 25.
Now, this is JavaScript. Okay, totally
different from the bad kind of
JavaScript, which is JavaScript. Okay,
JavaScript, JavaScript, JavaScript,
JavaScript. One's terrible, one's what
we're looking at right now. You
understand? So, enjoy this moment. But
we have JavaScript finally uh arrived in
the language. Now what we want to do is
to wire our objects together. We just
think about that. So why would I do
that? Let's think about a very simple
example. Here's a customer service very
trivial simple toy example. And in order
for my work in order to do the work I
need to do, I might have a database. I
can inject that into the constructor
like so. Add a constructor. And that's
just object-oriented programming. I'm
telling uh I'm saying I need a data
source. I don't care if it's a Postgres
or MySQL or whatever. I could describe
the configuration for the application in
a single class like this. I could say
customer service and then define it like
that. And here I have the benefit of
having all the wiring for my application
in a single place. So now if I want to
change something as I might for example
when I'm using a test uh framework I can
you know refactor the single thing and I
don't have to change everything in the
place where I'm using it. I don't care
that this is a mock in one place and a
postgrad in another. It's just a data
source, right? And I can stipulate that
this has a dependency on another thing
by defining it as a parameter there. So
now you can imagine somebody could go
along create an instance of this in
public static void main and then call
the methods and then uh pass one
reference to the other and arrive at a
completely built program. But what I
really want is the framework to do that
for me because as I say I can use that
framework to decorate or to add
capabilities uh to my application. So
here's going to I'm going to call this
app configuration and I'll use spring
frameworks at configuration annotation.
Uh here we are. There's that. And now I
can uh decorate these methods with at
bean. Okay. So at bean and I've got two
different bean definitions. These are
methods that return instances of
objects. Uh and um spring will
automatically run this configuration
because it's decorated with that
configuration. It'll say oh you created
a data source and this thing requires a
data source. I'll take the return value
of this method and pass it into this for
me. So now I have a fully instantiated
customer service and I've written my
code in such a way that the recipe for
that creation is sort of easy to
understand. Okay. So now what about this
customer service? I'm actually um
instantiating the customer service here
manually. But you can do it by
convention as well, right? You can tell
Spring, hey, I want you to discover
so-called stereotype annotations like
this. This is a marker annotation. And
Spring will look at that and go, okay,
this is a bean. It's got this marker
annotation. It's got a dependency that's
a data source. I happen to have a data
source over here and so it'll create the
instance of this kind of like I just did
here explicitly but it'll do so
implicitly. Okay, so I'm moving up. Now
of course I want to be very clear about
the logical rule of this thing in the
architecture. So I can use a stereotype
annotation. This annotation is the same
as at component in that it is annotated
with at component but it's a it's a
stereotype annotation. Okay. So it tells
spring this thing plays the role of a
service. You can use at component in
this case. It's logically not a big
difference, but it's just more clear
when you understand the logical nature
of the thing. Now, okay, this is a
service. I'm going to use a database. I
could work with a low-level JDBC data
source, but that's a terrible
abstraction with which to work. So,
going back to our pillars here, we've
got portable service abstractions that
make working with data sources a lot
nicer. So, rather than using the the
low-level JDBC data source, I can use
the Spring Framework JDBC client. I
forgot to add that to the class path.
Uh, so let me just add that here.
JDBC. JDBC. Here we go. Right. And I go
back over here. Now I've got the JDBC
client on the class path. And the JDBC
client is much easier to use. It's a a
fluid DSL. And I can use it to I can say
this.db.sql
select all from, you know, whatever.
Select all from customer. And I can pass
in the parameters. And I can pass in a
mapper to to uh map the results back
into an object that makes sense. and
it's very very object-oriented and very
clean and what I'll get is a list of
customers here right that's exactly what
I want so much more high level much more
focused that's the idea of a portable
service abstraction so in very quick
order we've used spring to wire things
up to to provide dependency injection
we've looked at aspectoriented we
haven't looked at that yet we'll talk
about that in a second and we've also
looked at portable service abstractions
where would uh aspectoriented
programming come into play well let's
say I had a method in here that returned
a new customer now what's a customer I
create that here int id string name.
Okay. And it can return a a customer
string name, right? Well, if I want to
implement that, that might be a thing
that actually talks to a data store. And
that data store, that data store uh you
know, I can do multiple writes at the
same time. And if something goes wrong,
I want to return uh and and and abort
the whole write. I don't want to have an
invalid state. So, I can use
transactions. Well, that's a a concern,
but it's not related to my business
logic. What I want to do is create an
entity in the database of type customer,
but I want it to be transactional. So I
can use for example at transactional.
This is a concern that I'm decorating my
service with. I'm adding it to the
method and Spring will envelop this
method invocation in a transaction. If
you throw an exception, it'll roll back
the transaction. If you don't, it'll
commit it. Right? And so that's a nice
highle thing that I can express in a
fluid way without affecting the
signature and the shape of my object. So
now I've got portable service
abstractions, aspect-oriented
programming, and dependency injection.
And then finally, you know, I might want
to have a web server. I might want to
have that database connection
automatically configured for me. So I
could create that like here, I went out
of my way to create the data source
manually, but that's a lot of stuff and
that's work that you know if I wanted to
do a production worthy data source with
connection pools and all that. This
would be very very tedious. So I want
some conventional easy way to do that.
Maybe I could just specify a password
and a username uh like that and I could
specify the URL and and I'd get an
actual, you know, with just a little bit
of configuration. Spring has all it
would need to do the job for me. So why
couldn't it? And that's what Spring Boot
gives you is auto configuration. It will
do that work for you. And the result is
now when I write this code, I have a
service. I've declared a dependency on
JBC client. I've got declared a
transaction management in there. Uh and
that's it, right? It just works. So I go
back over here and restore it like that.
Make that a spring boot application and
uh you know the concerns that I care
about the who's going to set up my
transaction management, who's going to
set up the data source, all that stuff
is just done for me. And the results is
I write very little code. So if you
understand these five these four
pillars, these four uh corners of this
spring rectangle, then you can
understand what we're going to look at
in spring AI to it. Let's talk about
that.
>> I'm exhausted already.
>> Me too. Just wanted to make sure we're
on the same page. It's a framework.
Okay. It's a framework for doing
frameworky kind of things and it's in a
nice language. It's very concise and
very easy to use. So let's go back now
and build our Spring AI application. Now
this is always where we have trouble,
right? This is as people who do demos.
We're always struggling with what do we
talk about? What could be our sample
domain? Something that people could
relate to. And obviously I think some of
you might know this famous Spring Pet
Clinic sample application. This is a
sample application that's been around in
the Spring ecosystem for decades.
Literally decades. But don't be cons
don't be confused though. This was
updated as recently as last week. And it
has to do with animals, dogs and and and
cats and uh you know, cute little little
critters and all that. And I love I love
animals. I mean, you love animals,
right? We all love We all love animals,
right? And I and I love I I just I just
I just I love them so much. I just love
just I just love all
I just love I just love all
all just I mean all
all
animals. Okay. almost all of them except
except one. Uh uh my dog was was
terrible. Not not a good boy. Okay, we
we actually that's not even true. I we
loved him. We just didn't like him. You
know what I'm saying? He was not a good
dog, but he was our dog. And we loved
him and we gave him a h a home because
all dogs, even terrible terrible
terrible dogs, deserve loving homes. And
so his name, by the way, was was Peanut,
right? Peanut was a uh not not a good
boy, but he was our dog, right? And we
kept him for for for three very simple
reasons. The first of which is is even
terrible, terrible, terrible dogs
deserve loving homes. That's a bedrock
fact. See what I did there with with the
uh the bedrock the AI model. Anyway,
it'll come it'll it'll it'll it'll it'll
arrive later. Anyway, there's that. And
then uh and the second reason is ego.
Okay, just going to be 100% honest with
you. In my home, my partner and my
daughter both speak five languages. I
only three. So, if we didn't have that
stupid stupid dog, uh then I would be
the stupidest in the house. And that
that will not stand. And it is with
great regret that I say that he's no
longer with us. So now I guess that
means that I am
>> Yeah.
>> We're gonna need to adopt a new dog.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And that's where that's kind
of where we're here, right? And then uh
part three, the third reason is I'm just
going to be 100% honest with you here,
just being real. He uh he he he is like
oh so cute, right? I mean, just look at
that dog. He was he was so cute. I so
cute. I know. Very very cute. Uh uh um a
very very cute dog, but but evil, okay?
Not not a good dog. I mean, look at
those blood crazed eyes, right? He was a
he was an evil little dog. And so so he,
you know, very very cute but evil. And
he reminds me of another dog about which
I learned during the pandemic named
Prancer. Now Prancer, you know, Prancer
was a dog that uh whose owner was trying
to find a new home for this uh this poor
doggo back in 2021, April 7th, 2021. And
she described this dog. She says, "Okay,
I've tried. I've tried for the last
several months to post this dog for
adoption and make him sound palatable.
The problem is he's just not. There's
not a very big market for neurotic,
man-hating, animal-hating,
children-hating dogs that look like
gremlins. But I have to believe there's
someone out there for Prancer because
I'm tired and so is my family." Every
day we live in the grips of the demonic
Chihuahua hellscape he has created in
our home. So, I think about this dog a
lot, right? This is borderline doggy
slander. And yet she continues. She
says, "I was excited to see him come out
of his shell and become a real dog. I'm
convinced at this point that he's not a
real dog, but more like a vessel for a
traumatized Victorian child that now
haunts our home." She continues,
she continues, "We already addressed the
men and children situation. If you have
people over, he would have to be put
away like he's a vacuum. I know finding
someone who wants a Chucky doll in a
dog's body is hard, but I have to try."
and she signs off warning, "Oh, he's
only 2 years old and will probably live
to be 21 through pure spite." And to be
fair, super cute. I would totally pet
that dog. I would lose a finger, but I
would pet that dog. That's a cute dog.
And so, I think about this dog and my
other my my dog a lot, right? They're
they live rentree in my head. And um you
know, by the way, this dog actually did
get adopted, right? So, this dog went
viral. Here's uh uh People magazine
talking about how Prancer, the demonic
Chihuahua, says new new owner, says he's
helped her heal from past trauma. Yeah,
super cute, right? Uh and then here's uh
USA Today. Okay, here's a demonic
Chihuahua Hellscape. Meet Prancer, the
puppy everyone wants after a brutally
honest Facebook review. Here's uh
Buzzfeed. We caught up with Prancer, the
viral nightmare Chihuahua. We find a
story of redemption.
And of course, uh, you know, slow news
day, I guess. New York Times, Prancer,
the demonic Chihuahua.
Come on,
Prancer of the Demonic Chihuahua finds a
home. So, again, this dog went viral.
Eventually, he did get adopted. But I
want I want to like build a thing so
that other people can adopt terrible,
terrible dogs, right? And so, in in
order to undertake that journey, we have
to make some decisions. We're going to
use an AI because we want people to be
able to go to our fictitious dog
adoption shelter and interview the
shelter uh for dogs in the shelter.
Obviously, most people don't find their
dogs by looking at the news, right? That
would be if your dog is so so infamously
terrible that he's in the news, you're
doing something wrong, right? So,
instead, they're going to go to a
shelter.
>> Yeah. So, we're going to help people
adopt dogs with AI. Great place to use
AI. And the models that we're going to
be using are on Amazon Bedrock. There's
like uh let's see, did you pull up the
model page? No. Um
>> on Bedrock, you can choose from 249
different models. Uh we're going to be
using the Amazon first-party ones, but
there's the anthropic cloud models,
there's the DeepSseek models, there's
the open um uh GPT OSS models, lots of
different models to choose from. So
that's our model side. That's what we're
going to be using. That's what you're
going to be using when we get into the
hands-on piece. And then we're going to
use Spring AI to provide the interface
to the LLM for the user to go find the
dog of their dreams
>> or nightmares.
>> Or nightmares.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, lots of
different models here. Uh you mentioned
you got like jet brains, you got chat
the open AI ones, you've got all the
>> so many different ones to choose from
>> third party and first party ones all uh
all here. So we are we're going to go
back to our uh spring initializer and
we're going to build a new project as
always start.spring.io. We're going to
call this assistant to help with uh to
help with assisting people to help find
a dog of their dreams or or nightmares.
And the reason we're going to call it
assistant is because I'm amazing uh with
names. Okay, I'm great with names. I get
that from my dad. My dad was amazing
with names. When I was a small boy, we
had a small white dog and my father
named him White Dog. Again, just really,
really good with names. Okay. So, so
we're going to add that. We're going to
add the web support. We're going to add
uh bedrock. Right now, what are we what
are we adding here, mister?
>> So, in our sample application, we're
going to be doing rag, which is going to
use vector embeddings, and we need an
embedding model on uh bedrock in this
case to do the embeddings. We'll talk
about what that actually means and how
it works in a little bit, but we need
the bedrock support for the embeddings
and then we need the bedrock converse
support for the chat interface to an
LLM. So, two different libraries that we
use u for those two different features
that we're going to add into the
application.
>> Sounds good to me. We have a question
about which database to use. I mean,
it's 2025. What database would you use
by default if you had no other choice?
>> I love Postgress.
>> I do too. Now, Postgres is a great
choice, but I'm also going to need a
vector store, right? And a vector store
is logically a separate component but
they can be you know a lot of existing
data stores and data data store in
infrastructure support vector store
capabilities. So logically I could go
here and I could say you know let me use
a purpose-built vector store like mil or
pine cone we cudrint uh uh you know
chroma uh you know all these different
ones type but there's also a bunch of
existing database infrastructure uh that
can be used as a vector store. So for
example, MongoDB, Gemfire, Elastic
Search, Couchbase, Patrick, Cassandra,
uh, uh, Reddus and Oracle and Postgres,
MySQL, Neo forj, etc. So, we're going to
use Postgres as a vector store. There's
a mod, it's basically just a plugin that
you load into a stock standard Postgres.
It gives you vector capabilities. So, PG
vector, we're going to use some chat
memory here, JDBC. Uh, and I think we
need the actuator. I think that's it.
>> Uh, Spring Data.
>> Yep, we need that. Thank you. spring
data JDBC and hit go. Okay,
>> so that's just our dependencies for the
full application that we're going to
build. You're going to also use I think
many or all the same dependencies in the
workshop. So we'll see how we use these
in the next few minutes and then get you
hands-on.
>> Right. So first things first, let's
connect let's specify some configuration
here uh which I have managed to
conveniently uh not include here.
>> Sorry. Should we be configuring this or?
>> No, no, just pay attention and
>> just we're giving you the background
information that you're going to need
and then we're going to set you loose on
the workshop so that hopefully when you
get in the workshop, you know what all
the pieces in code and everything is
doing.
>> Just a whole bit for you.
>> Who that's fun. Hopefully that endpoint
wasn't powered by Cloudflare.
Okay, so here's some uh configuration.
What is all what have we've just done?
>> So there's a few things we did configure
in here. Uh the first one is our chat
model. We're going to use the Nova light
model. That's just a a super lightweight
uh inexpensive fast one. So, and then
we're enabling that chat model. We're
also specifying the embeddings model so
we can do the vectorzation. And we're
using the bedrock cohhere model for that
one. We have to specify the dimensions
to align the dimensions from the
language model to the PG vector store.
We initialize a schema to store it in.
And yeah, what else in there do you want
to say?
>> Uh database. We have a SQL database
running in the background here. It's
Postgress. We're going to connect to it.
You would normally not stipulate your
username and password in a property
file. You'd use cloud native like
environment variables, that kind of
thing. Uh so export,
there you go. You would do something
like that. But for now, for our demo,
we'll just keep them in the property
file. Okay. So
system,
>> we got our config. So that was using
that auto configuration stuff that Josh
talked about. just by setting those
config properties. There's a bunch of
functionality that gets added into this
application that we're going to be
building. Okay. So, the first thing that
we're going to do is set up uh just a a
basic controller, a web controller
that's going to allow us to make a HTTP
request to the controller and then make
a call to the LLM. So, call to a
controller, call over to the LLM. To do
that, we set up the chat client. The
chat client is the chat uh interface in
SpringAI to talk to an LLM.
>> I'm a big fan of the chat client. It was
written by only the best people. Okay,
the actual best people worked on this
code and I trust them implicitly. Okay,
really really good code. Moving on. So
anyway, here we go.
>> Okay, so the chat client based on auto
configuration that was in that
properties, it's going to know how to
connect to Bedrock. Josh has already set
up his AWS credentials and so that that
piece is already done. Uh but then we've
got the chat client. We have to we use
the builder to build it and then we can
use the chat client by calling the chat
client and then prompt giving it a user
prompt and then calling it what was it
content and that's it. So you now you
can send your HTTP request to that web
server. And when we do that
>> okay
>> yay that's a response from the LLM. So
>> we got a dial tone right? We got a dial
tone few lines of configuration and we
all the configuration you just saw only
like two of those lines in the
configuration were to get to this point.
We just threw all the configuration for
everything that we're going to show you
in um but two lines of configuration and
like six lines of code and we're talking
to a LLM.
>> Yeah. And uh you know really the AI
stuff is just these four lines of code
which I hit enter for. So it could have
been one line and nobody would have
complained. Okay. Now uh we passed in
the user question. That's the user
prompt. That's the thing that each uh
user will ask the model. Okay, now this
is working. We've established a dial
tone. It says, "Hey, Josh. Nice to meet
you. If there's anything you'd like to
talk about or you have any questions,
feel free to let me know." Great. We're
connected. Let's just make sure
everything is is working. Everything is
happy. So, let's just uh let's just
confirm, you know, what's my name?
And by the way, if it gets this wrong,
it's going to get it wrong for two of us
in the audience today, not just me.
Okay. So, it says, "I'm sorry, but I
can't tell your name as it's personal
information that I don't have access
to." Awkward. Okay, we just met and it's
already forgotten me. Why does this
always happen to me? I don't know. I
don't know, but I don't like it. Uh,
what's happened here fundamentally,
this API is stateless, and we need to
give it access to a transcript of
everything that's been sent. So, we're
going to use the Spring AI concept of an
adviser, which is like an interceptor
that allows you to pre-process and
post-process requests.
So the advisor allows us to as Josh said
intercept the actual call to the LLM and
then this gives us the chance to then
store the whole conversation in memory.
And so we're going to use our database
through JDBC the Postgress database that
we already uh configured and and pulled
in the the libraries for and then we're
going to set up memory to that database.
So this will allow us to every time we
call the LLM push the some portion of
the past history into the LLM with every
new question being asked. Uh so you set
up the the memory advisor, you've set up
the backing store to store the memory.
Uh I think we're using the windowed
memory or something like that. Yep. So
it's going to have a a set uh number of
messages that it's going to keep. By
default, it keeps the user messages and
the messages coming back from the LLM.
Those are called like the assistant
messages. So we keep uh all that in
memory and so the next time we ask a
subsequent question it's going to know
or it's going to not really know it's
going to send again the history.
So we got your JDBC store set up. Uh I
think in properties we told it to like
automatically initialize the the data
the data source. So that's all good.
>> Yep.
>> Um
>> okay. Should we try it?
>> Yeah. And then you added your advisor to
the chat client.
>> Yep.
>> Great.
>> Yep. So, uh, let's connect to the data
source just so we can see what's gone
gone here. Okay. Hit apply. Hit okay.
Refresh database public tables. Spring
AI chat memory. Delete that from the
last run. Goodbye. Actually, let's just
delete everything except for that table.
>> Okay.
>> Don't delete your dogs.
>> Nope. Do not delete the dogs. We need
them.
>> We need those dogs.
>> They are very important. Reload. Okay.
So, we got one table. I'm going to
restart the program. It'll now
initialize the Spring AI chat memory,
which is now empty. Now we can ask it.
Okay. Uh my name is Josh. Fine. Nice to
meet you.
And then what's my name? Okay, good.
Hello Josh. It's remembered me. Right.
So this is good. We've got we've
established the transcript and that's
being p persisted here in the Spring AI
chat memory. Uh now this is it's good
but it's still unfocused. Right? It's
just basically a wide open uh uh um like
hole pointing straight to my bedrock
account. Right? I I have I want
>> the kids will do their homework with
this chatbot with our adoption service.
So, we want to like give it a little bit
of focus, right? This isn't as good as
like a a full-on agentic framework, but
it's a bit of a focus. So, we're going
to give it a system prompt. Okay. And I
actually happen to have a pre-written
system prompt. Okay. So, I shall go over
here. Desktop MISK talk system prompt.
I'm just going to cat it. And then wait.
No, no. I'm so sorry.
Much better. Okay. So, we'll take that,
put it into the clipboard, and uh we'll
Here we go. Here's our system prompt.
Okay. And uh we shall configure that
here. System system. Now, this system
prompt is as follows. You're an AI
powered assistant to help people adopt a
dog from the adoption agency named Pooch
Palace with locations in Antworp, Souls,
Tokyo, Singapore, Paris, Mumbai, New
Delhi, Barcelona, San Francisco, and
London. Did I Did I say Antworp? I I
meant
>> That was like a month ago.
>> Yeah, we're totally different people
now. Moving on. So, we've given it a
system prompt. We told it what we want
to do. Let's see now if that changes its
behavior when we ask it questions that
it might or should or could maybe
answer. Do you have any neurotic dogs?
Now, mind you, we're we're trying to
build a service to help people adopt
dogs. Hi, Josh. We currently don't have
any dogs listed as neurotic. However, we
have a variety of different dogs with
different temperaments and
personalities. If you're interested, I
can provide more details about the dogs
at our various locations. Okay. It's
acting like it's meant to be able to
answer our question, but for whatever
reason, it just can't yet. Okay. And
that I think we know why.
>> Yeah. It doesn't have any data, right?
It doesn't know our dogs.
>> Exactly.
>> Introduce the AI to our dogs.
>> So, I'm going to set up yet another
advisor.
>> So, for this one, this is where we're
getting into rag. And the general
architecture that Josh is going to
implement here in a few lines of code is
an advisor that's going to be able to to
intercept the prompt and then based on
the prompt do a similarity search with
some data in our vector store and then
based on the results from that
similarity search put what could come
back from that into the prompt that then
we send to the LLM. So this is
traditionally uh called the rag pattern
and this just provides a way for us as
the developer to inject data in. We'll
get into tools later where the LM makes
a decision on when it needs data, but
this is us deciding that we're going to
put data into this prompt. Essentially,
it's going to go over to the LLM. So to
set this up, you've created your you're
creating your dog. So that's going to be
the the record that we store this the
dog uh dogs with on the application
side. We're going to need to be able to
pull our list of dogs out of our
database. So you set up the dog
repository. And then what else do we
need here? We need to inject. So back to
dependency injection from the the
fundamentals of Spring, we're injecting
that an instance of that dog repository
in. And notice that there was no all we
ever defined for that dog repository was
just an interface. But uh Spring is
going to create an implementation of
that interface for us and give us that
instance here when we when this uh
assistant controller is constructed.
>> And notice that I'm just using random
arbitrary strings here. I'm not giving
it a particular schema. Don't need to.
I'm also just passing in a singleton
list. It's a list with one element in
it. Um and you know, if you have large
bodies of text, you might pass in you
might tokenize it. You might split it.
And Spring AI provides a whole hierarchy
to support with that. Uh but we're just
going to use one right now because
there's a small amount of text. One
thing I noticed is that this is a a
document uh for dogs. So I shall call
this document. Okay. And there we go.
And uh finally I've configured question.
Let me explain that one real quick that
part cuz we need to get the vectorzed
forms of our dogs because that's how we
do the similarity search against them.
And we need a language model to do that.
So that's why we had to configure the
cohhere in our case embedding model that
actually runs on the cloud. It's an LLM,
right? It's we give it a string and it
gives us back a vectors. And so we need
to get those vectors so that then we can
match the user prompt against those
vectors so that we can get to the dog
that the user is going to ask about. And
so Spring AI includes the rag support
which allows us to call the uh the
embedding LLM uh and then store those
embeddings into our vector database. And
so and then did you add the adviser?
is going to intercept that request, go
over to do the similarity search against
our our vector store, and then put the
results into our prompt automatically
for us.
>> Okay. And it says, "Yes, we do have a
dog named Prancer who's described as
neuronic." Great. So, it found our buddy
Prer. We're in a good place. But
obviously, this is just a paragraph full
of text. You may very well want that to
be given back to you in a form that you
can uh uh use in the rest of rest of
your system, right? So I can actually do
some like OM kind of thing for my uh dog
the responses from the model. So I'm
going to take this type rather than
asking for the string response from the
model I'll ask for a strongly typed
representation of that structured output
mapping
and I'll ask the same question again and
this time I get strongly typed JSON
back. Right? So this is a lot nicer if
you it's a strongly typed integer. I can
use that to do correlation and all that.
Now in my case I actually want the
string response but I wanted you to know
that the other thing was possible. Now,
what would I do next?
>> Okay, so we got the data coming in. Uh,
and that's all good. We got the rag set
up. The next part is going to be to be
able to actually schedule an adoption
with this uh with the adoption service
to be able to get Prancer and and pick
them up, right?
>> Yeah. Okay. So, I'm going to build a
service here called dog adoption.
And it's just going to be a service.
It's going to have a method here that
will help give a a point in time in the
future where we can come by the shop and
pick up the dog. Okay. So, I'm going to
say var I equals instant now. And I'll
just hardcode a date 3 days hence.
Right. So, we're not actually hooked up
to a scheduling system. So, we're just
like faking the scheduling system. And
then what we need to do is take this
schedule method and tell the LLM about
the schedule method so that when a user
asks about doing scheduling, it can then
direct our agent, our AI agent to then
call the schedule method. And so to do
that, all we have to do is add a at tool
annotation. We have to make sure we
specify a description that's in natural
language because that's what's going to
indicate to the LM when it needs to
actually call that tool. So you've added
the description. we've annotated it with
that tool. We can also annotate the
parameters so that it knows how to fill
in the actual parameters to call in that
tool. Um, and that's I think all we need
for our tool on the definition side. And
then we do need to wire it into our chat
client so that our chat client then
knows about the tool. Uh so the tool
definitions they go into the prompt that
we send to the LLM so that the LLM then
knows here's the options that I have
available. If it decides that what the
user is asking for can be accomplished
with a tool call then it responds and
says all right call this tool. We call
that tool in on the agent side and then
we send the results of that tool call
back to the LLM in a subsequent call. So
all that gets handled with when Josh
added the with tools
>> found prancer at pooch palace. Right.
And now
let's adopt Prancer.
Okay.
Okay. Uh November.
>> So you set it for Yeah. 3 days from now.
So great. That's it. So it called our
tool. We've kind of validated there that
sure enough we made that request and it
did all the LLM calls and the tool calls
and created the scheduling uh called the
schedule system uh tool and then
responded back to us. So
>> So now what if I wanted to repurpose
this from other what if I wanted to
repurpose that business logic from other
AI integrations, right? I'd use
>> Yeah. So MCP you've probably heard of
this is a technology to take that tool
that we've done there and put it out on
an external system and so we can create
an MCP server for that tool. So instead
of having it run in the same process as
the agent, we can have it external. Nice
thing about MCP is it's not just for the
tools that we want to build and
integrate with. It can be for all sorts
of other providers that have provided
their MCP servers or you know tons of
open source and off-the-shelf MCP
servers that we can also integrate with
our chat client. So it creates this this
standard protocol to do the tool calls
that we just saw there. So Josh has just
taken the tool that we defined in the
agent, pulled it out into a separate
project. So we can run it as a
essentially remote server and you're
running on a different port, port 8081.
So now you've got your MCP server for
that scheduling tool uh up and running.
We did replace the annotations with ones
that are are specific to an MCP server.
So there's MCP tool and MCP ARG. those
add additional parameters beyond just
the at tool uh that are specific to MCP
because there's some things that make
sense in a remote, you know, MCP server
that don't make sense in a local server.
>> And if I use the MCP inspector, you can
see there's a tool called schedule. It's
got a dog ID and a dog name. Great.
>> So now we can definitely consume and
connect to that MCP service, but I want
to connect to it from our Spring AI
client. Going back over here, now we're
going to refactor this code to instead
point to that remote MCB service.
>> Uh let's do the Oh, yeah. Take that out.
>> MCP sync. No, sync MCP. Nope. I have to
add
>> Did we add the MCP client?
>> Let's just check.
>> Yeah.
>> Nope. Add the starter. Come on.
>> So, there's a dependency in Spring AI
for MCP servers and one for MCP clients.
We just added the MCP client one. And
now we can use that dependency injection
to inject into here a uh MCP toolback
provider, the sync MCP and uh
>> it's
okay.
>> One of these.
>> This one.
>> That there it is.
>> That's got to be it.
>> Yeah.
>> Feels a little short. Is that the right
one?
>> Well, we'll find out.
>> We'll find out.
>> Okay. I'm going to configure that here
as a callback.
What's the uh thing we're looking for
here?
>> Oh,
can you Okay, take a look at your thing
here quickly.
>> I do have the code.
>> This is new in 1.1, by the way.
>> Yeah, 1.1 of Spring AI just came out and
um
so we're still getting used to the
changes in it. Well,
worst case I can do MCP client.
>> Oh, you can. Did you do the config yet?
>> What do you mean
>> the config to connect to the server sign
events?
>> You mean the property? The No, I can do
that right now. Yeah.
>> Okay. Yeah, do the property while I look
up the
>> Okay. Uh
client SSC connections
URL equals HTTP localhost 8081 SSE,
right?
>> Yep.
>> Okay. Okay, then there's your class.
Sync MCP tool call back provider.
>> Ah, rolls right off the tongue. How
could I have forgotten? Sync MCP
>> tool call back
>> callback provider.
>> H Why isn't it popping up? Oh, there it
goes. Okay,
>> so easy.
>> So easy.
>> Okay, put that in there. Put that there
and then reload.
Okay, now we're going to try the same
query, but bear in mind we've got the
agent on the left. We've got the MCP
service on the right. Uh, and it's going
to answer queries about the scheduling.
And the thing on the left is going to
answer questions about dogs. Okay, let's
now try this here.
>> Oh, yeah. Sorry, man. Here.
>> Oh, it's fine.
>> So, here we go. We're going to try this
again.
Okay. Do uh let me delete the One thing
you should be aware of is these models
can sometimes uh
>> they like to cheat if they've got memory
of something already.
>> Yep. So okay uh we have Prancer. Great.
When can I pick up Prancer from the New
York City pooch pass location? Says uh
201121.
And you can see that it called the MCP
service over here. Great.
>> Uh and invoke that. So the AI model has
agency. It has the ability to make
decisions based on uh the query that the
user sent to it. It says, I've got this
tool available to me to answer this
question that I'm not otherwise prepared
to answer, which is when can I schedule
a pickup from a pooch spouse location?
And it did that on its own by calling
our tools. We also gave it access to our
data. This is one of the key wins, one
of the key opportunities we have here
which is all most of the data in your
enterprise and the organization is
guarded by spring by programs written on
the JVM and in spring. If you can give
access to that to your AI models, you
can build amazing things without having
to rebuild all that stuff just to be
able to add these AI integrations.
Right? So I think with that we'll let
you loose. you should be able to.
>> So, yeah. So, I'm going to give you some
instructions on the actual hands-on part
now. So, I'll switch over to to my
computer. Um, but, uh, everything that
you just saw, you're going to do just in
a different context. Uh, so the code's
going to be about a unicorn store. Um,
and we're going to help you, you know,
make sure you get all that up and
running and working on your machine. So,
give me one sec to switch over. While
I'm switching over my laptop, any
questions about Spring and Spring AI,
anything that you've seen there? Um, not
not uh did did we make things more
confusing? Um,
>> yeah.
>> And Drew has a mic if you
>> happy to answer any questions,
>> anything. Okay. All right. Almost ready.
Like I'm what I'm hoping is that some of
you have come from the Java community
and you're sort of familiar with Spring
Boot and all that. But I'm also really
hoping that some of you are coming from
a different ecosystem and uh you know
you're you're you're rightly feeling a
little sort of discombobulated because
you haven't seen this stuff before.
Happy to answer questions. Hopefully it
was clear but it was it is a new thing.
I get it. You know
>> I have a pair of socks if anybody has a
question
for socks.
>> We saw we somebody told us the best
story about this. What?
>> Uh I guess there somebody was not these
particular socks, but I guess somebody
was like allergic to metal or something.
>> Oh,
>> for and so they what happened? Oh, some
engagement. They they got engaged.
>> Do you Were you there when we heard what
you're talking about?
>> Somebody
we we gave away some of these socks some
at one of the recent shows we were doing
and somebody came up to us and said uh
that their partner was allergic to
metal. So they for went an engagement
ring
>> over
engagement socks and they were AWS
socks, right?
>> I don't know about that, but that'd be
very very great,
>> you know.
>> Okay, no questions. Okay, well then
let's get started on the workshop.
>> Yep. No questions.
>> Here's what you need to do. You need to
point your browser to that URL,
s12d.comspring-ai-native-com.
And then I'm going to show you the first
few steps, but then all of the material
for the workshop is in there, and I'll
I'll show you how that how that works.
So get that URL in there.
Give you another minute to do that.
and how these instances that we've only
got a limited amount of time together
here. Okay.
>> I put 48 hours on the clock uh starting
at I don't know or something.
>> So even if like we don't get even if you
don't finish the workshop in the next
hour or whatever it is we've got left
today, you've still got another 36 hours
or so.
>> You can just yeah keep rolling. The only
request that I make is don't mine
Bitcoin or put any personal information
on these instances. Then I get in
trouble. Um, okay. So, when you go to
that URL, you should see this screen.
Uh, you can choose any of those three
options. If you're an Amazon employee, I
guess that's the only time you can use
that third option. Uh, but I'm going to
use the easy option, which is email a
one-time password. So, you need access
to your email. And I have access to my
email.
>> Imagine.
>> Uh, oh, first I need to put in my actual
email, which feel free to email me if
you have questions. Oh, yeah.
jamesjames.com
>> or josh joshhlang.com
>> and then let me get my verification
code.
So obviously this is your email and your
verification code.
>> Yeah, don't use his.
>> So once once you've done that process
and got signed in, then you'll see that
there is some terms and conditions that
Yeah, I don't know. You'll have to read
those on your own. I agree to them. Uh
and then join the event.
Um, okay. So then once we're in, this is
the actual workshop and all the content
for the workshop is right in here. And
so there's a few things that I want to
point out. Uh, first is that all of the
workshop content is in this menu up here
on the left, which is a little hard to
see at my um large enlarged font here.
Um, but the first the first page that we
get to is this top left button here. And
there's one important thing on this this
page. So before you navigate away from
this page, down at the bottom of it,
this is a VS Code web environment that's
in this AWS account that I've created
for you. And we want to open that up
because all of the work that we'll do
with code is going to happen in that VS
Code environment. So I'm opening that
URL. I need to copy my ID password and
put that in. And then this will launch
my code environment that I'm going to do
all the rest of the stuff with. We've
got the terminal. Um, so you know, you
can do your terminal, you can uh write
code, all that kind of stuff in there.
Then the actual workshop starts at this
building Java AI agents with Spring AI.
And this is really just an overview of
all the the content and the
architecture. And it's all the stuff you
just saw in Josh and I's presentation.
It's got the rag, it's got the um the
chat memory, it's got the MCP stuff, and
then there's workshop sections that
you'll go through. So, first you'll do
some setup, then you'll create the
application, do the chat client, create
the rest controller, create a UI. Uh the
one that this one has actually has a
nice chat UI unlike Josh's, you know,
curl or HTTP, whatever. Uh no UI there.
Um, so there's all these different
different sections that you'll go to.
When you get to deploying on AWS, things
start to get more advanced and then
observability gets significantly more
advanced. Um, so these, as Josh said,
these accounts are available for 48
hours. So you can, you know, get as far
as you want through these.
>> One day, 18 hours left.
>> That okay. One, one day, 18 hours left.
So that's how much time you have left
with this account. And then I will um
point out one thing in here is that we
added for uh just recently this embabel
section to the workshop and uh this is
an interesting technology that's built
on top of uh on top of spring AI and
actually Alex here works uh on embable.
So if you have questions about he's the
expert in the house. Um so embable is
this another layer on top of spring AI.
So you saw like the chat client and the
rag and the memory and all that kind of
stuff. But what about orchestration of
agents? How do you build kind of larger
more complex agents on top of spring AI
and Abel is created by Rod Johnson who
actually created Spring framework. So
he's pretty knowledgeable in that area.
He's created this agentic framework uh
called Embabel. So there's a whole
section of the workshop on doing the
embabel piece and the agent
orchestration.
>> Bonus material.
>> You still have the deployment stuff in
there.
>> Yeah, I mean everything's in there. So
they
>> we got we got deploy to AWS. You can do
it with EKS, ECS, Lambda. Um we're we're
going to get agent core new service in
there as well. But
>> do we still have the issue with the
routing? They have to do the memory.
>> No, I got it fixed. Look at that. Look
at that. Local memory then external
memory. Yeah, this we did this workshop
yesterday and we encountered a couple
bugs. Just like two.
>> Yeah, just two.
>> Two. And so we fixed those bugs. So
>> we did that in San Francisco. So that
was a different time, a different place,
a different space. We're different
people now. can't stand in the same
river twice, you know.
>> So, is that making sense? Let me pull up
that URL again. Um, is that making sense
for for the workshop? Uh, I'm sure you
all work at different paces, so you can
go. Uh, we're here till 5:35.
>> On the dot
>> on the dot. We we have to head out right
at 5:35 to the New Jersey Java user
group tonight. Um, but we're here if you
have questions, if you have problems,
uh, if things don't make sense, um, let
us know. We're here to help make sure
that you can get all your, you know,
your Spring AI stuff all built.
>> And if you want to have like a longer
version of this discussion, you can join
us tonight in New Jersey or tomorrow at
the New York Java SIG here in town or
we're doing a 25minute talk here at the
show.
>> Well, tomorrow, don't come to our talk
tomorrow here because it's the same one
you just saw.
>> You just saw you're go to something
else.
>> Skip our talk tomorrow.
>> Go to something else tomorrow. Don't
come to ours. Um, okay. you'll be
disappointed.
Okay. So, any problems so far? People
making progress
>> working. Okay. Okay. We're here. Uh
raise your hand, grab us if you have
questions or problems.
>> Yeah. Feel free to like holler because I
we can barely see you because we got
spotlights burning into our eyeballs.
>> Just yell prancer. We're there.
>> Yeah. Prancer. No.
Is this yours? That's yours. This is
mine.
Oh, and there's some incentives. First
person that gets the chat client
working, just dial tone, gets a pair of
socks. So, you know, soon as you get
working, claim claim your socks. First
person. Maybe we'll throw in some other
spiffs along the way, too.
Good questions. Those get socks. But
let's see how many socks I have. Four.
Five socks. Five pairs.
Hey everybody,
>> you did it. You survived. What do you
think?
>> You made it.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
Uh,
>> all right. Did you all learn something?
>> You get through the whole entire thing.
Kubernetes, observability, and Babel,
all the things. That's like an all day
workshop.
>> It is.
>> Yeah.
>> And we know that because we just did it
as an all day workshop uh yesterday.
>> Yeah.